We will study the establishment of the gastrointestinal tract
and the peritoneal cavity and the peritoneum
in the development of the stomach, the duodenum, the intestine, and the colon.
We will start by understanding it in the development of the stomach
in relation to the liver and spleen and the
pancreas.
Let’s clearly understand the initial phase, what we call the delimitation of the embryo.
We have seen the integration.
of this external coelom into an internal coelom.
We arrive at this stage.
And here, we can see both in the sagittal view
and in the transverse view.
We can clearly see the integration of my peritoneal cavity.
Do not forget the synchronicity of development.
One last image to see this integration.
The main driver is growth,
it is the formation of our body,
but it is elsewhere.
primitively, the overall growth of my embryo, the wrapping and the return
to my line
midline. When you take a small baby, you hold him in your hands and he shows you
the entire history of his embryology. You just need to follow the tissues. It’s
a three-dimensional movement, even into a fifth dimension.
I mean
by the fourth dimension, time. The fifth dimension, I mean, is this energetic,
electric component.
that underlies the entire system.
Do not forget that this movement is always integrated within this upward phase
of my ectoderm
and the relative downward movement of my endoderm, with this phase
almost at heart level.
The ascent of the ectoderm and the descent of the endoderm and the integration of the
heart
stretch the pouches of the diaphragmatic musculature and those of the future
muscles.
This means that to treat and reorganize this entire space, you will need to
understand that it is necessary to treat and release the diaphragm, because it is what will create
this overall delimitation.
The ascent of my neural tube, the development of
my peritoneal cavity, the establishment of my heart is
a movement that will reintegrate globally towards a focal point.
that we call the umbilical cord. One could say that the umbilical cord,
in its finality, contains the history of this development, of
this unfolding, of
this delimitation, of this reorganization of your peritoneum.
It will integrate into specific rotation movements, organized in
clockwise
and counter-clockwise directions. On a frontal plane, we will see
a
global developmental counter-clockwise movement. On a
transverse plane, we will see a
clockwise developmental movement. This peritoneal cavity will begin to organize,
to delineate.
This means it will move, and in this movement, you must learn to follow this
development. First, there is the peritoneum that surrounds an organ. It’s
called visceral peritoneum.
When a peritoneum...
attaches an organ to the
posterior side, it is called
a mesenterium. If it is the stomach,
it will be called greater omentum.
If it is the duodenum, it will be called
the mesoduodenum. If it is
a colon, it will be called the mesocolon.
Or, depending on
the location, it will be called
a Toldt’s fascia, for example.
But if it’s a
small intestine, it is called
a mesentery.
The peritoneum that has the...
Here, there is the posterior part, which is called the posterior parietal peritoneum.
At the lateral level, it’s called the lateral parietal peritoneum,
the anterior parietal peritoneum.
If it’s a peritoneum that connects one organ to another, it is
called an omentum.
For example, you have the lesser omentum, it is a tissue that connects the liver to the stomach.
You also have an omentum that connects the spleen to the stomach.
An omentum, a meso, is always a double layer that carries
in the middle a vessel.
But in the developmental movement, we will see that there will be folds and a reorganization
to the extent that the omentum here, for example the meso, will be able to come to the side
like this.
And so here, there is a tissue that will attach, and it will form a
adhesion fascia.
This is something that surgeons can easily resect because there are no vessels.
A meso always contains a vessel.
While a ligament or a fascia does not necessarily contain a vessel.
At the level of the peritoneum, we will have the mesoderm, the somatopleure, the splanchnopleure,
the ventral mesogastrium...
and we will have what we call mesos, fascias, omenta that we call
epiplons or ligaments.
All of this is the hyperperitoneum, we can say, initially organized in the peritoneal cavity, I
talk.
There is my intestine that will begin to grow, there is my liver that will develop,
there is my stomach that wants to express itself, there are my lungs that are pushing.
All of this needs to find its place.